- Hey everyone, this is Daniel for Ruck the JVM
みんな、こんにちは。Rock the JVMのDanielだよ。
and this video will introduce you to Scala3 macros.
この動画ではScala 3のマクロを紹介するよ。
Now, this is a video that has been requested
この動画はずっとリクエストされてたもので、
for a lot of time and in this video,
長い間お待たせしてたんだけど、
you're going to learn how Scala macros work
Scalaのマクロがどう動くのか、
and why they're useful.
そしてなぜ便利なのかを学んでいくよ。
So here, you'll have the opportunity to try out
ここでは、今まで書いた中で
some of the most magical Scala code that you'll ever write.
一番「魔法みたい」なScalaコードを試す機会があるよ。
So the assumptions are that you are comfortable
前提として、Scalaに慣れていること、
with Scala, obviously, and that you know what inlines are.
当然だけど、それとinlineが何か知っていること。
We recently made a video on the Ruck the JVM channel
最近Rock the JVMチャンネルで
on how inlines work.
inlineの動画を出したからね。
Obviously, the best way to make use out of this video
この動画を最大限活用するには、
is to run this code and experiment yourself
実際にコードを動かして自分で実験するのが一番だよ。
and also refer to this video or to the article at the blog
あとで振り返りたくなったら、この動画かブログの記事を
with the link in the description
参照してね。リンクは概要欄に
if you want to get back to these topics.
貼っておくよ。
Now, this topic is something that I talk about at length
さて、このトピックは僕の
in my Scala macros and metaprogramming course.
Scalaマクロ＆メタプログラミングコースで詳しく扱ってるんだ。
This is a long form course on pretty much everything
メタプログラミングについて必要なことを
you need to know about metaprogramming.
ほぼ全部カバーした長編コースだよ。
So the ability to create statically typed correct Scala code
つまり、静的に型付けされた正しいScalaコードを
at compile time dynamically depending on what you need.
コンパイル時に動的に生成する能力のことだね。
So this course will get you all the skills
このコースを受ければ、
you need to become a true Scala wizard
本物のScalaウィザードになるための
and be able to write productivity tools for yourself
スキルが全部身につくよ。自分やチームのための
or your team with macros and the most magical parts of the Scala language.
生産性ツールをマクロとScala言語の最も魔法的な部分を使って書けるようになる。
We write several thousand lines of code in the course
コースでは数千行のコードを書くし、
and we also have two projects that will get you to appreciate both the magic of Scala
2つのプロジェクトを通じて、Scalaの魔法のすごさと、
and also the kind of work that tooling and library authors do for the community.
ツールやライブラリの作者がコミュニティのためにやっている仕事のありがたさを実感できるよ。
So if you're interested, I'm going to leave a link in the description.
興味があれば、概要欄にリンクを貼っておくね。
These are skills that only a select few people have like the Scala compiler team and a few others who learned on their own
こういうスキルを持ってるのは、Scalaコンパイラチームとか、独学で身につけた少数の人だけなんだ。
like myself and other contributors and library authors in the Scala ecosystem.
僕自身もそうだし、Scalaエコシステムのコントリビューターやライブラリ作者たちとかね。
So I thought it would be great if more people have these skills which is why I've made this course
だからもっと多くの人がこのスキルを持てたらいいなと思って、このコースを作ったし、
and which is why I'm recording the video that you're watching right now.
今見てるこの動画を録画してるわけなんだ。
And speaking of which, let's go back to our own problems and let's discuss what macros are.
さて、本題に戻って、マクロとは何かを話していこう。
So this is an SBT project that I've made from scratch.
これはゼロから作ったSBTプロジェクトだよ。
You can create a Scala empty project yourself.
自分でも空のScalaプロジェクトを作れるよ。
I only added a Scala compiler option to print whatever is inlined.
僕はインライン化された内容を表示するコンパイラオプションだけ追加したんだ。
So I added this compiler option -X print post inlining and also added the mask inlines to 100,000.
具体的には -Xprint:postInlining というオプションと、maxInlines を100,000に設定した。
This is really excessive, but it won't hurt for this particular project.
100,000はかなり過剰だけど、このプロジェクトでは問題ないよ。
So if you want to make an SBT project from scratch, these are the settings that I use.
SBTプロジェクトをゼロから作りたいなら、これが僕の使ってる設定だよ。
I also will leave a link to the GitHub repository of this video in the description.
この動画のGitHubリポジトリのリンクも概要欄に貼っておくね。
All right, so what are macros?
さて、マクロとは何か？
Macros are a technique for metaprogramming.
マクロはメタプログラミングのための技法だよ。
And metaprogramming means that you can manipulate a well-formed program
メタプログラミングっていうのは、正しく構成されたプログラムを操作して、
and obtain another program which is in some way better.
何らかの意味でより良いプログラムを得るってこと。
And so Scala macros are a way to manipulate Scala code and obtain other Scala code within the Scala language,
Scalaマクロは、Scala言語の中でScalaコードを操作して別のScalaコードを得る方法なんだ。
which is kind of an inception way to look at it.
ちょっとインセプションみたいな話だよね。
But let me try to make a little bit more sense.
でも、もう少しわかりやすく説明してみるね。
So let's assume that we aren't dealing with a Scala language,
Scala言語ではなくて、
but we're rather dealing with a very simple programming language, and I'm going to use the scientific calculator as an example.
もっとシンプルなプログラミング言語を扱っていると仮定しよう。関数電卓を例に使うよ。
So let's say that you write text, which is in the syntax of a scientific calculator, like 2 plus 3 divided by 4 plus 2 times 8 or something like that.
例えば、関数電卓の構文でテキストを書くとする。2 + 3 ÷ 4 + 2 × 8 みたいな感じで。
And that is a proper expression that you send to the calculator to say compile and run, and that will give you the final result.
これは正しい式で、電卓に送ってコンパイル＆実行すれば、最終結果が得られるよね。
Now, in order for the calculator to compute the sort of expression, it has to parse it out, and it has to figure out which operations need to execute first and which it has to execute later.
電卓がこの式を計算するには、まずパースして、どの演算を先に実行して、どれを後にするか判断しないといけない。
So if we were to design a programming language that would represent expressions like this, we would define some sort of interface, and I'm going to use Scala code to do that.
こういう式を表現するプログラミング言語を設計するなら、何らかのインターフェースを定義するよね。Scalaコードで書いてみよう。
I'm going to have a trade expert, and I'm going to have some case classes for all the potential operations that we might want to support for calculator language.
trait Exprを作って、電卓言語でサポートしたい全ての演算のcase classを定義するよ。
So for example, I would say a case class for some, that would take, let's have a case class for a number first, let's say a number with a value, which is a double, let's say, let's say that the calculator works with doubles, and this extends expert, then we have some which has two expressions, one on the left hand side, which is an expert, and right hand side, which is an expert, and right hand side, which is an expert.
例えば、まずcase class Numを作ろう。Numはvalueを持っていて、型はDoubleとする。電卓はDoubleで動くとしよう。これはExprをextendsする。次にSumがあって、2つの式を持つ。左辺がExpr、右辺もExpr。
And this obviously extends expert. And we have a case class for some subtract, multiply, divide, okay, so we have some subtract, multiply, and divide. And maybe we want to have case classes for other kinds of operations like sine of 30. In this case, we'd have a case class for sine with an expression, as an expression, and this extends.
これも当然Exprをextendsするよね。他にもSubtract、Multiply、Divideのcase classがある。あと、sine(30)みたいな他の演算のcase classも欲しいかもしれない。その場合、Sineのcase classで式を受け取って、Exprをextendsする。
Expert, and so on and so on and so forth. Okay, so you get the idea. Now, in order for the calculator to evaluate this expression, it will have to parse it out into a data structure that resembles something like this. So for this particular expression, that would be something along the lines of a sum, where the left hand side is the number two, and the right hand side is another sum, where you have the left hand side, the division between three and four,
という感じで続くんだ。さて、電卓がこの式を評価するには、こういうデータ構造にパースする必要がある。さっきの式なら、Sumになって、左辺がNum(2)、右辺がまたSumで、その左辺がDiv(3, 4)、
So div with number three, and number four, then we have the right hand side, the multiplication, so we have a multiplication, where the left hand side is a number two, and the right hand side is another multiplication, where the left hand side is number eight. So num eight, and then we have sine with num 30. Okay, so this data structure,
つまりDivでNum(3)とNum(4)。右辺はMultiplyで、左辺がNum(2)、右辺がまたMultiplyで左辺がNum(8)、そしてSine(Num(30))。このデータ構造が、
that would resemble the kind of natural mathematical expression that I wrote here at the top. This, my friends, is called an abstract syntax tree, or an AST for short, and any programming language will have to resort to an AST to be able to describe what is possible in that language.
最初に書いた自然な数学的表現に対応してるんだ。これは抽象構文木、略してASTと呼ばれるもので、どんなプログラミング言語でも、その言語で何が可能かを記述するためにASTを使う必要があるんだ。
So for a language like Scala, the class definition, or a value definition, or method definition, or mathematical expressions, or method invocations, or pretty much everything else that you can express in Scala, can and will be represented by a node in an AST. And our goal as a macro programmer in Scala is to manipulate these ASTs into other ASTs that will then later be compiled to something that can be executed on the computer. So the way that a compiler works is that you have like the text language, so text,
Scalaみたいな言語では、クラス定義、値の定義、メソッド定義、数式、メソッド呼び出し、その他Scalaで表現できるほぼ全てがASTのノードとして表現されるんだ。そしてScalaのマクロプログラマとしての目標は、これらのASTを操作して別のASTにし、最終的にコンピュータで実行可能なものにコンパイルすること。コンパイラの仕組みは、テキストから
compiled to an AST, and then to a binary, and then to a binary, obviously, in a very, very high level. So every programming language will have a some sort of interpreter that will semantically and syntactically analyze your code into a data structure that it can then evaluate, or compile to a binary that will give the computer rules to evaluate a data structure like that.
ASTにコンパイルされて、それからバイナリになる。もちろんこれは非常にハイレベルな説明だけどね。どんなプログラミング言語にも、コードを意味的・構文的に解析してデータ構造にするインタープリターがあって、それを評価するか、コンピュータがそのデータ構造を評価するルールを持つバイナリにコンパイルする。
So the modern programming languages have more than just two compiler phases. The Scala language has several dozen phases, but in general, the process looks something like this. Now, macros give us the ability to manipulate the AST before it turns into a binary. So if you want to expand the sort of process, you have text, and then AST, and then some sort of black magic that manipulates the AST into a better AST, and then that turns into a binary.
現代のプログラミング言語にはコンパイラフェーズが2つ以上ある。Scalaには数十のフェーズがあるけど、一般的にはこんなプロセスだよ。マクロは、ASTがバイナリになる前にそのASTを操作する能力を与えてくれるんだ。プロセスを展開すると、テキスト→AST→何らかの黒魔術でASTをより良いASTに変換→バイナリ、となる。
So that is where we step in. So macros are the ability to process ASTs that the Scala compiler successfully parsed at that point, and turn that AST into another kind of AST that we can process as we see fit, and then that successful AST is then further down processed into the compiler pipeline into a binary.
僕たちが介入するのはそこだ。マクロは、Scalaコンパイラがその時点で正しくパースしたASTを処理して、好きなように別のASTに変換する能力なんだ。そしてその新しいASTがコンパイラパイプラインでさらに処理されてバイナリになる。
Now the trouble is that once an AST has been built, we don't have access to the same source code, the same Scala code to be able to process that AST into another kind of AST, which is why macros or AST manipulation has been historically hard for compiled languages like Scala and Java and stuff like that.
問題は、ASTが構築された後は、同じソースコード、同じScalaコードにアクセスしてそのASTを別のASTに加工できないってこと。だからマクロ、つまりAST操作は、ScalaやJavaのようなコンパイル言語では歴史的に難しかったんだ。
AST manipulation is very hard once you leave the host language, which is what happens once you obtain the AST, you lose the ability to interact with the host language, up until Scala 3, which gives us the ability to process well typed AST in the same language.
AST操作は、ホスト言語を離れると非常に難しくなる。ASTを取得した時点でホスト言語と対話する能力を失ってしまうんだ。Scala 3までは。Scala 3が、型付けされたASTを同じ言語で処理する能力を与えてくれたんだよ。
So the way that macros work is that if you want to get into a back door to access the same language and process your AST, you can obtain an AST from a Scala expression, which is a piece of text, to obtain an AST via a process called quoting,
マクロの仕組みはこうだ。同じ言語にアクセスするバックドアを手に入れてASTを処理したい場合、Scala式からASTを取得する。それがテキストからASTを得る「クォート」というプロセスで、
and then manipulate that AST and obtain a new AST, and then reinsert that AST back into the compiler pipeline via a process called splicing.
そのASTを操作して新しいASTを作り、そしてそのASTを「スプライシング」というプロセスでコンパイラパイプラインに再挿入する。
So this process essentially lengthens the compiler pipeline, but gives us the ability to process well typed AST at compile time.
このプロセスは本質的にコンパイラパイプラインを延長するけど、コンパイル時に型付けされたASTを処理する能力を与えてくれるんだ。
Let me give some examples of how that would work.
どう動くか、例を見せるね。
In order for a macro to work, we need these two pieces, quoting and splicing.
マクロが動くには、クォートとスプライシングの2つが必要だ。
Quoting is the ability to take a Scala expression and turn that into one of these expert data structures that we can manipulate with the same language.
クォートは、Scala式を受け取って、同じ言語で操作できるExprデータ構造に変換する能力のこと。
Now, once we're ready to reinsert that AST back into the compiler pipeline, that action is called splicing.
操作済みのASTをコンパイラパイプラインに再挿入する準備ができたら、それがスプライシングだ。
So let me demonstrate an easy example of a macro.
じゃあ、簡単なマクロの例を見せるね。
So all macros are inline methods.
全てのマクロはinlineメソッドだよ。
So you know by now that inlines simply copy the method implementation at the call site.
inlineは単にメソッドの実装を呼び出し箇所にコピーするって知ってるよね。
So let's have an inline method, let's say first macro, get out of copilot.
inlineメソッドを定義しよう。firstMacroとしよう。Copilotは無視して。
And let's say that this takes two pieces of arguments, let's say a number as an int and a string as a string and this returns a string.
引数を2つ取る。numberはInt、stringはStringで、Stringを返す。
Now all macros will be the splicing of a quoted piece of code.
全てのマクロは、クォートされたコードのスプライシングになる。
So we're going to do a splice of and this is the syntax for splicing dollar and then curly braces much like string interpolation.
スプライシングの構文は、ドル記号と波括弧だよ。文字列補間とよく似てるけど、
This is just code interpolation.
これはコード補間なんだ。
Okay.
OK。
And the interpolated code is going to be an expression obtained by some implementation of this macro, which is usually done in a separate method.
補間されるコードは、このマクロの実装から得られる式で、通常は別のメソッドで行う。
Let's call this first macroimple and the implementation is going to take expressions of these types.
firstMacroImplと呼ぼう。この実装はこれらの型のExprを受け取るよ。
And the representation of the kind of stuff that you can write in scale is very similar to the toy example that we did for the calculators.
Scalaで書けるものの表現は、電卓のおもちゃの例ととてもよく似てるんだ。
The piece of AST is still called expert.
ASTの部品はやっぱりExprと呼ばれる。
It takes a type parameter.
型パラメータを取るよ。
So I'm going to comment these out and I'm going to have let's call this a num AST number AST, which is an expert int and the expert type needs to be imported from the package scala dot quoted.
これらはコメントアウトして、numASTという名前にしよう。これはExpr[Int]で、Exprはscala.quotedパッケージからインポートする必要がある。
Or simply quoted because all the Scott packages are naturally imported in all projects.
あるいは単にquotedからでいい。scalaパッケージは全プロジェクトで自然にインポートされてるからね。
So you can say import quoted star and this num AST takes an expert int and let's say a string AST as an expert string.
import quoted.* として、numASTはExpr[Int]、そしてstringASTはExpr[String]とする。
And the only kind of value that you can obtain from a macro implementation is going to be an expert of something else.
マクロ実装から得られる値は、必ず何らかのExprになる。
Let's say we have an expert string and I'm going to leave it unimplemented for now.
例えばExpr[String]としよう。今は未実装にしておくね。
And this is the manipulation part.
ここがASTの操作部分。
So this is manipulating the AST and this is quoting plus reinserting the AST back as an expression.
そしてこっちがクォート＋ASTを式として再挿入する部分だ。
So I'm going to quote the first macro impl and in order for me to turn this number into an expression and turn the string into an expression,
firstMacroImplをクォートするよ。numberを式に変換し、stringも式に変換するには、
I will need to quote them.
クォートする必要がある。
So I'm going to add a single quote number and single quote string.
シングルクォートをnumberとstringの前に付ける。
This is the quoting part.
これがクォート部分だ。
So quoting turns these expressions into experts that we can then manipulate in the method.
クォートで式をExprに変換して、メソッド内で操作できるようにする。
And then whatever expert we obtain as a result, we inject it back into the code via splicing.
結果として得られたExprをスプライシングでコードに注入する。
So quoting and then splicing, that's the macro pattern.
クォートしてからスプライシング、これがマクロのパターンだ。
Now in order for us to use a macro, we need to go into another file to be able to call this first macro because due to how Scala is compiled, we need to have the macros separate from the usage of those macros.
マクロを使うには、別のファイルに移動してfirstMacroを呼び出す必要がある。Scalaのコンパイルの仕組み上、マクロの定義と使用は分離する必要があるんだ。
Now one other thing that is important for any macro implementation is to pass a given value called quotes.
あと、マクロ実装で重要なのは、Quotesというgivenの値を渡すこと。
So I'm going to say using quotes with a capital Q, this is a data structure that gives you access to the macros API, which also gives you the ability to create expressions at compile time like dynamically create expressions.
using Quotes（大文字のQ）と書く。これはマクロAPIへのアクセスを提供するデータ構造で、コンパイル時に動的に式を作る能力も与えてくれるんだ。
So let me go save this, let me go to the usage file, and I'm going to have my let's say first macro usage.
保存して、使用側のファイルに移ろう。firstMacroUsageとしよう。
And this is going to be my first macro, first macro, and I'm going to import macros demo, everything so that I have access to that method first macro with some expressions like two plus three and the string Scala.
MacrosDemoの全てをインポートして、firstMacroメソッドにアクセスできるようにする。式として2 + 3と文字列"Scala"を渡そう。
Okay, let me go save this.
OK、保存しよう。
Unfortunately, metals doesn't give me any information on whether this code compiles or not.
残念ながらMetalsはこのコードがコンパイルできるかどうか教えてくれないんだ。
Thankfully, I have an SBT terminal running behind the scenes.
でも裏でSBTターミナルが動いてる。
And this is the source of truth.
そっちが真実のソースだ。
And we have accession occurred by executing macro expansion because an implementation is missing.
マクロ展開の実行中に例外が発生してる。実装がないからだね。
So in other words, this question mark is actually being invoked and evaluated at compile time.
つまり、このクエスチョンマークが実際にコンパイル時に呼び出されて評価されてるってことだ。
And this is something that's very important.
これはとても重要なポイントだよ。
All macro implementations and macro invocations are executed.
全てのマクロ実装とマクロ呼び出しはコンパイル時に実行される。
So this code, this method is invoked at compile time.
つまりこのコード、このメソッドはコンパイル時に呼び出されるんだ。
So if I happen to build an expression myself like expert with this is a simple string, this expression will be evaluated at compile time.
もし自分でExpr("this is a simple string")みたいな式を構築すれば、この式はコンパイル時に評価される。
And this expression will be assigned to my first macro usage variable.
そしてこの式がfirstMacroUsage変数に代入される。
So if I happen to save these files, metals doesn't give me an indication, but SBT does show me what's happening here.
ファイルを保存すると、Metalsは何も教えてくれないけど、SBTが何が起きてるか見せてくれるよ。
So now we have a code success.
コンパイル成功だ。
And look at this.
見てみて。
We have first macro usage, which is a string.
firstMacroUsageがStringになってる。
And we have this is a simple string.
そして"this is a simple string"になってる。
This evaluation happens at compile time before the code is even turned into by code.
この評価はコンパイル時に、コードがバイトコードに変換される前に起きるんだ。
Okay, so a few lessons so far.
OK、ここまでのまとめ。
All macros have this sort of shape inline methods with a bunch of arguments.
全てのマクロはこういう形をしてる。引数を持つinlineメソッドで、
And the implementation is always some splicing of some expression.
実装は常に何らかの式のスプライシング。
And that expression is usually calling a method with quoted expressions.
その式は通常、クォートされた式を引数にメソッドを呼び出す形だ。
And the macro implementation is a regular scholar method that takes a bunch of arguments.
マクロ実装は通常のScalaメソッドで、引数を取るんだけど、
Instead of regular values, you take experts of values.
通常の値ではなく値のExprを取る。
And then you can manipulate these experts and build any sort of expert that you like.
そしてこれらのExprを操作して、好きなExprを構築できる。
Cool.
いいね。
And this method happens or is executed, evaluated at compile time.
そしてこのメソッドはコンパイル時に実行・評価される。
Now, instead of simple expressions, let's build some more complex ones.
じゃあ単純な式の代わりに、もっと複雑なものを作ってみよう。
Let's say that we want to evaluate at compile time what this int is.
このIntがコンパイル時にどんな値か評価したいとする。
So if this int happens to be a constant, then we can evaluate it and you can do some checks with it.
もしこのIntが定数なら、評価してチェックできるよ。
So for example, I can say val num value as numast dot, there's a method called value or abort.
例えば、val numValue = numAST.valueOrAbortと書ける。
If this expression is not a constant, then this will issue a compile error.
この式が定数でなければ、コンパイルエラーになる。
Let's say val string value as a string ast dot value or abort.
val stringValue = stringAST.valueOrAbortも同様。
And let's do some sort of check for example, val new string as if num value is bigger than three, then I'm going to say string value dot repeat, num value.
何かチェックしてみよう。例えば、val newString = if (numValue > 3) then stringValue.repeat(numValue)
Okay, and maybe otherwise, I'm going to say string value dot take num value divided by 10 or something like that divided by two.
そうでなければ、stringValue.take(numValue / 2)とか、そんな感じで。
Ignoring the potential problems of having the too short string and stuff like that, you can deal with that particular logic.
短すぎる文字列の問題とかは一旦無視して、そのロジックは自分で対処してね。
And let's assume that the expert returns the macro impl is and then you have the plus new string returned as a result.
マクロ実装が返すExprとして、Expr("the macro impl is " + newString)を返そう。
So let's go save this.
保存しよう。
And if I go back to the compiling output, we see that the first macro usage is the macro impl is scholar repeated five times.
コンパイル出力を見ると、firstMacroUsageは「the macro impl is ScalaScalaScalaScalaScala」、つまりScalaが5回繰り返されてる。
That's because the number AST, which is the expression two plus three is evaluatable at compile time.
numAST、つまり式2 + 3がコンパイル時に評価可能だからだ。
This is very important.
これがとても重要なポイント。
And the num value is bigger than three.
numValueは3より大きいので、
So we have string value repeats in our case five times.
stringValueがこの場合5回リピートされるんだ。
If this expression were more complicated and unable to be evaluated at compile time.
もしこの式がもっと複雑でコンパイル時に評価できなかったら...
So for example, if I have a method, let's say compute meaning of life, meaning of life returns an int and let's say it returns 40 plus two.
例えば、computeMeaningOfLifeっていうメソッドがあって、Intを返して40 + 2を返すとする。
And you say compute meaning of life instead of two plus three, this will trigger a compile warning, a compiling error.
2 + 3の代わりにcomputeMeaningOfLifeを渡すと、コンパイルエラーが発生する。
That's because this compute meaning of life expression cannot be computable at compile time in the general terms.
computeMeaningOfLifeという式は一般的にはコンパイル時に計算できないからだ。
So this expects a known value.
これは既知の値を期待してるんだ。
This is why we get this compiling error.
だからコンパイルエラーになる。
So I'm going to simply reduce that to something that is evaluatable at compile time and simple math expressions are.
コンパイル時に評価可能なものに戻そう。単純な算術式は評価可能だからね。
So the value or abort method will trigger a compile error if this is not computable at compile time.
valueOrAbortメソッドは、コンパイル時に計算できない場合にコンパイルエラーを発生させる。
All right.
よし。
Cool.
いいね。
Now, there are many things that you can do with expressions, many things that you can do with these ASTs.
さて、式でできることは沢山あるし、ASTでできることも沢山あるよ。
And in the macros course, the macros and metaprogramming course, I talk at length about what you can do with these experts.
マクロ＆メタプログラミングコースでは、Exprでできることを詳しく話してるんだ。
This is a bit outside the scope of this video, but I want to show you some capabilities.
この動画の範囲外だけど、いくつかの機能を見せたいと思う。
For example, quoting, quoting and quote matching.
例えば、クォートとクォートのパターンマッチング。
So let me show you what I mean by this.
どういう意味か見せるね。
I'm going to create a macro.
マクロを作るよ。
So I'm going to have an inline method.
inlineメソッドを定義しよう。
Let's call this a pattern matching on options.
pmOptionsと呼ぼう。Optionに対するパターンマッチングだ。
I'm going to have an option as an option int.
引数としてoptをOption[Int]で受け取る。
And I'm going to mark this parameter inline so that we can see the actual expression inside this option that we're passing this argument.
このパラメータをinlineにマークして、渡される引数の中の実際の式が見えるようにする。
And I'm going to splice and I'm going to call a PM options impl.
そしてスプライシングで、pmOptionsImplを呼ぶ。
Notice that this naming convention is pretty standard.
この命名規則はかなり標準的だよ。
You can see this in various libraries and various implementations in the scholar ecosystem.
Scalaエコシステムの様々なライブラリや実装で見かけるパターンだ。
And I'm going to quote the opt that I receive as argument.
引数として受け取ったoptをクォートする。
Then I'm going to have a method PM options simple, where we are going to have an option as an expert of option int, I'm going to have using quotes.
pmOptionsImplメソッドを定義する。optionはExpr[Option[Int]]として、using Quotesを付ける。
Okay, and this is going to return, let's say an expert string.
OK、戻り値はExpr[String]としよう。
Okay, now this expression contains the entire structure of the option int that we're passing this argument.
この式には、引数として渡したOption[Int]の構造全体が含まれてるんだ。
So the expression itself, so for example, if I'm calling, say, option description, let me put some question marks here.
例えば、optionDescriptionを呼ぶとする。ここにはクエスチョンマークを置いておこう。
Or let me introduce an expert, let's say, to do, so that the code doesn't crash.
いや、Expr.todoにしよう。コードがクラッシュしないように。
Okay, so option description as PM options on some option like sum2.
OK、optionDescriptionとしてpmOptionsにSome(2)みたいなオプションを渡す。
If I pass sum2 as argument directly as it is, and the option parameter is inline, the expression itself, the constructor sum2, is being described by this expert option int.
Some(2)をそのまま直接引数として渡して、optionパラメータがinlineなら、式そのもの、つまりSome(2)というコンストラクタがこのExpr[Option[Int]]で記述される。
So the descriptor of the expression itself is what is being passed here.
つまり式自体の記述子がここに渡されるってことだ。
So you see here that the option description is currently to do, that's because the macro implementation returned the expert.
見てみると、optionDescriptionは今はtodoになってる。マクロ実装がExpr.todoを返してるからだ。
Now the expert itself, as I mentioned earlier, contains the description of what was used earlier in the code to build this expression.
Expr自体には、先ほども言ったように、コード内でこの式を構築するのに使われた記述が含まれてるんだ。
Hopefully that makes sense.
ここまでOKかな。
And that description can be pattern match.
そしてその記述はパターンマッチできる。
For example, I can say opt match.
例えば、opt matchと書ける。
And let's say, let me create, actually, let me run an implementation where I'm going to return a string.
実装を書こう。Stringを返すようにする。
So let's call this result as opt match.
val result = opt matchとしよう。
And I'm going to have my expert result as the final value.
最終値としてExpr(result)を返す。
Okay, so value result, opt match.
OK、val result、opt match。
The expression itself can be pattern matched.
式自体がパターンマッチできるんだ。
And I can pattern match against a quoted expression like this.
クォートされた式に対してパターンマッチできる。こんな風に。
So quote with curly braces is the opposite of splicing.
quote（波括弧付き）はスプライシングの逆だ。
And I can destructure a pattern match with whatever constituents this expression was built out of.
この式がどんな構成要素から作られたかでパターンマッチを分解できるんだ。
So I'm going to say, for example, sum with 42.
例えば、Some(42)に対してマッチさせる。
So if I'm passing the constructor sum 42 explicitly as it is, this pattern match will match.
コンストラクタSome(42)をそのまま渡せば、このパターンにマッチする。
So I'm going to say, got the meaning of life.
その場合「got the meaning of life」を返そう。
In case I get a quote for sum with some sort of variable, and if you pattern match on quotes, you'll have to do the reverse of matching, which is the dollar variable.
次に、何らかの変数を持つSomeにマッチする場合。クォートに対してパターンマッチするときは、マッチングの逆、つまりドル変数を使う。
So the expression that you're going to pattern match against, this is going to be an expression, an expert that you can then use later.
パターンマッチする式は、後で使えるExprになるんだ。
So I can say, got a variable, got a variable.
「got a variable」と書こう。
And you can also use s interpolated strings inside code that evaluates experts.
Exprを評価するコード内でs補間文字列も使えるよ。
And if you want to print this out, there is a thing called x.show.
式自体を表示したい場合は、x.showというものがある。
So you can print out the expression itself.
式そのものを出力できるんだ。
And in case you get anything else, let's say got something else.
それ以外の場合は「got something else」としよう。
Okay.
OK。
So let's consider this sort of implementation.
じゃあこの実装を考えてみよう。
In the macros demo usage, I have option description with PM options sum two.
使用側では、optionDescriptionとしてpmOptions(Some(2))を渡してる。
Now the constructor sum two is going to pattern match the second case with got a variable.
Some(2)というコンストラクタは、2番目のcase「got a variable」にマッチする。
And it's important to note that the constructor sum two itself has no resemblance or has no knowledge of how this will be represented in the bytecode.
重要なのは、Some(2)というコンストラクタ自体は、バイトコードでどう表現されるかとは関係ないってこと。
So currently, PM options with sum two should match the second case.
今のところ、pmOptions(Some(2))は2番目のcaseにマッチするはず。
Let's check the compiling output.
コンパイル出力を確認してみよう。
So we have option description, got a variable, and we have two.
optionDescriptionは「got a variable」で、値は2だ。
If you have something along the lines of option two, which at the runtime, say option description two, PM option with option two, even though at runtime, these two instances are going to be the same or at least comparably equal by the equal sign.
もしOption(2)のようなものがあったら、つまりoptionDescription2としてpmOptionsにOption(2)を渡すと、実行時にはこの2つのインスタンスは同じか少なくともequalsで等しい。
Or by the equals method in the JVM, the constructor itself, the expression itself is different.
でもJVMのequalsメソッドで等しくても、コンストラクタ自体、式自体が異なるんだ。
So PM options will not match either one of these cases.
だからpmOptionsはどちらのcaseにもマッチしない。
It's going to match the last one.
最後のcaseにマッチする。
So let me go save these files and you're going to see option description two is got something else.
ファイルを保存すると、optionDescription2は「got something else」になってるのがわかるよ。
It's important to understand that these constructors don't really know how they will be represented in the bytecode.
これらのコンストラクタがバイトコードでどう表現されるか知らないということを理解するのが重要だ。
This code simply pattern matches whatever expression or expression description was being passed literally in the code.
このコードは単に、コード内で文字通り渡された式、つまり式の記述に対してパターンマッチしてるだけなんだ。
Okay.
OK。
So this is something that the Scala Macro API offers us and pattern matching on quotes is something definitely new for most people.
これはScalaマクロAPIが提供してくれるもので、クォートに対するパターンマッチは多くの人にとって確実に新しい概念だと思う。
And I'm pretty sure that if you're watching this video, you'll probably find these as news.
この動画を見てるなら、これは初めて聞く話だろうなと思うよ。
And in the course, I talk more about what you can pattern match and what you can extract out of these quotes.
コースでは、何に対してパターンマッチできるか、クォートから何を抽出できるかをもっと詳しく話してるよ。
So these are super powerful and these allow you to manipulate ASTs by just pattern matching on the respective quotes.
これは超強力で、対応するクォートにパターンマッチするだけでASTを操作できるんだ。
And you can pattern match arbitrarily complex expressions.
任意の複雑な式にもパターンマッチできるよ。
For example, I can copy something like this, like option description three.
例えば、こんな感じでoptionDescription3をコピーしよう。
I'm going to say PM options on options 10 dot map underscore plus one.
pmOptionsにOption(10).map(_ + 1)を渡す。
So this expression itself can also be pattern matched.
この式自体もパターンマッチできる。
Currently, it returns got something else.
今は「got something else」を返してるけど、
But if we add a case here, I can show you how that looks like.
ここにcaseを追加すれば、どう見えるか示せるよ。
So in case we pattern match on some sort of option, I'm going to call this dollar O, which is an option of some type.
何らかの型のOptionにマッチする場合、$oと呼ぼう。Option[T]のTは小文字tとする。
I'm going to call this lowercase T and quotes can also pattern match types as well before the types are erased.
クォートは型もパターンマッチできるんだ、型が消去される前にね。
You can say map with some sort of other type like S.
Sみたいな別の型でmapすると言える。
So option A map with the type B with some sort of function.
Option[A]にmap(B)で何らかの関数を適用する形だ。
Then I'm going to say mapping an option.
その場合「mapping an option」を返そう。
Let me go save that.
保存しよう。
Okay, we have mapping a function with dollar, dollar F.
OK、「mapping a function with $$f」って出てる。
It's important to put the dollar signs for expressions.
式にはドル記号を付けるのが大事だよ。
Okay, so look at this.
見てみて。
We have mapping an option.
「mapping an option」と出てる。
And you can extract both the types.
型を抽出できるし、
You can extract the pieces of the patterns.
パターンの部品も抽出できるし、
You can extract functions.
関数も抽出できる。
You can invoke them dynamically and so on and so forth.
それを動的に呼び出したりもできるんだ。
There are a lot of things that you can do with quotes.
クォートでできることは沢山あるよ。
So quoting is a powerful feature.
クォートは本当にパワフルな機能だ。
And one other thing that I wanted to show you in this video is the so-called reflection.
この動画で見せたかったもう一つの機能が、いわゆるリフレクションだ。
Reflection gets a bad rap, at least in the JVM world, because reflection means inspecting things at runtime, which circumvents type safety.
リフレクションはJVM界隈ではあまり良いイメージがない。実行時に物事を調べるから型安全性を迂回してしまうんだ。
But in Scala, with macros, reflection also means type safety.
でもScalaでは、マクロによるリフレクションも型安全なんだ。
I'm going to show you what I mean by this.
どういう意味か見せるよ。
So a classical case of reflection is to invoke a method dynamically by name.
リフレクションの典型的なケースは、名前でメソッドを動的に呼び出すこと。
So you can simply mention the method name and the runtime just finds that method by name and just invokes that.
メソッド名を指定するだけで、ランタイムがその名前でメソッドを見つけて呼び出す。
You can do something like that at compile time in a fully type safe way by this reflection thing.
同じようなことを、コンパイル時に完全な型安全性を保ったままできるんだ。このリフレクション機能でね。
So I'm going to show you a little demonstration.
ちょっとデモを見せるよ。
Let's call this call method dynamically.
callMethodDynamicallyと呼ぼう。
And I'm going to have a type parameter a on an instance of type a.
型パラメータAを持ち、型Aのインスタンスを受け取る。
And let's say we have the method name, which is a string.
メソッド名はStringとする。
And we know for a fact that the method will take some sort of argument, which is an int and this returns some sort of string, let's say.
このメソッドはInt型の引数を取って、Stringを返すとわかっているとする。
Okay, and I'm going to splice, let's call this call method dynamically.
OK、スプライシングで、callMethodDynamicallyImplを呼ぶ。
I'm going to have an impel on the quote instance, quote method name and quote arc.
クォートしたinstance、クォートしたmethodName、クォートしたargを渡す。
Okay, let's define the call method dynamically impel, which has an instance.
callMethodDynamicallyImplを定義しよう。instanceは、
Now we need to type parameter a.
型パラメータAが必要だね。
So instance is going to be an expert a.
instanceはExpr[A]。
Then we have the method name, which is an expert string.
methodNameはExpr[String]。
And then we have the argument, which is an expert int.
argはExpr[Int]。
We have using quotes and this returns an expert string.
using Quotesがあって、Expr[String]を返す。
Okay, now let me start with a block.
OK、ブロックから始めよう。
Okay, and let me show you how we can use that.
そしてどう使うか見せるね。
So let's say we have expert to do.
とりあえずExpr.todoとしてコンパイルを通そう。
Okay, just to make this code compile.
OK。
And in the usage, I'm going to create a simple class like a case class.
使用側で、簡単なクラスを作ろう。case classを定義する。
So case class, say simple, simple wrapper with an X as an int.
case class SimpleWrapperとして、xをIntで持つ。
And let's say we have a magic method, which takes another parameter.
そしてmagicMethodを定義しよう。別のパラメータを取って、
And this returns an expression like this simple wrapper called a magic with, and I'm going to return, returning.
Stringを返す。"returning " + (x + y)みたいな感じで。
And I'm going to have X plus Y.
x + yを返すんだ。
Okay, and I'm going to have my val meaning of life and of my val result as call method dynamically on a simple wrapper 10, let's say.
val meaningOfLifeと、val resultとして、callMethodDynamicallyをSimpleWrapper(10)に対して呼ぶ。
So this is going to be the instance.
これがインスタンスになる。
The name of the method is going to be magic method.
メソッド名は"magicMethod"。
And the argument is going to be meaning of life.
引数はmeaningOfLife。
Okay, so meaning of life is obviously 42.
meaningOfLifeはもちろん42だよ。
And the result is going to be the invocation of this call method dynamically.
resultはこのcallMethodDynamicallyの呼び出し結果になる。
Now the benefit of something like this is that the name of the method can be built out of simple strings or fetch from the database or things like that.
こういうものの利点は、メソッド名を単純な文字列から構築したり、データベースから取得したりできること。
The runtime reflection has its uses, but at the compile time, the reflection that I'm talking about maintains type safety.
実行時リフレクションにも用途はあるけど、コンパイル時のリフレクションなら型安全性が保たれるんだ。
And if this method happens to not exist, then we're going to have a full compile error.
もしメソッドが存在しなければ、ちゃんとコンパイルエラーになる。
So currently, this result is going to return to do because that's what the expression returns.
今はresultはtodoを返す。式がそれを返してるからね。
And this call method dynamically now needs to be processed by me.
callMethodDynamicallyの実装を書いていこう。
Okay, now in order for me to access reflection at compile time, this quotes instance, I'm going to name it.
コンパイル時にリフレクションにアクセスするには、このQuotesインスタンスに名前を付ける。
So I'm going to have Q, which is quotes.
qとしよう。qはQuotes型。
And Q offers some methods that are in a special package called reflection.
qにはreflectという特別なパッケージにメソッドがある。
So or reflect, which we have to import.
これをインポートする必要がある。
So I'm going to have import Q reflect.
import q.reflect.*と書く。
And Q reflect gives us the ability to build arbitrarily complex abstract syntax trees without necessarily having the types of these expressions.
q.reflectは、式の型がなくても任意に複雑なASTを構築する能力を与えてくれるんだ。
And I talk more at length about the untyped abstract syntax trees in the macros and metaprogramming course.
型なしASTについては、マクロ＆メタプログラミングコースでもっと詳しく話してるよ。
So that's what I'm going to do.
じゃあやってみよう。
I'm going to have a look at this.
これを見てみよう。
I'm going to have a look at this one.
こっちを見てみよう。
And I'm going to have a look at this one.
こっちも見てみよう。
So the term untyped AST is called term.
型なしASTに対応するものはTermと呼ばれるんだ。
Now the term untyped is not really proper because the term is also properly typed in the Scala type system.
「型なし」というのは正確じゃないんだけどね。TermもScalaの型システムで適切に型付けされてるから。
It's just that the term gives us less types to worry about.
ただTermを使うと、気にする型が少なくて済む。
And it gives us more loose access to a bunch of functionalities that expert A does not.
Expr[A]では提供されない機能に、より緩くアクセスできるんだ。
So even if this model is slightly inaccurate, at least at the beginning, it's useful to think of these concepts in this style.
このモデルは若干不正確だけど、少なくとも最初はこの考え方で理解するのが役に立つよ。
And in our case, to be able to access a method, quote unquote, reflectively, so dynamically by the method name,
今回のケースでは、メソッドにいわばリフレクティブに、つまりメソッド名で動的にアクセスするために、
we need to turn this expert into a term.
このExprをTermに変換する必要がある。
So I'm going to have a valid term as instance dot as term.
val term = instance.asTermと書こう。
Now, the as term method is granted on an expert A if we have this import in scope.
このasTermメソッドは、このインポートがスコープにあればExpr[A]で使えるようになるんだ。
If we don't, then we don't have access to this method.
インポートがなければ、このメソッドにアクセスできない。
And you can inspect terms with an arbitrary precision.
Termは任意の精度で調べることができるよ。
So I can say valid method is to find a method using a select term.
Selectを使ってメソッドを見つけることができる。
So I can say select dot unique.
Select.uniqueと書けるんだ。
So essentially, I'm grabbing a member of this expression, which happens to be the method name.
本質的には、この式のメンバーを掴んでるんだ。そのメンバーがメソッド名に当たるわけだね。
So I'm going to say select unique on the term.
Termに対してSelect.uniqueを呼ぶ。
This is the expression that I'm inspecting and the method name dot value or abort.
これが調べている式で、methodName.valueOrAbortでメソッド名を取得する。
So this is going to be a string and I'm returning a select object and this select object gives us the ability to invoke that method.
これはStringになって、Selectオブジェクトが返される。このSelectオブジェクトでメソッドを呼び出せるんだ。
So the application or the invocation is going to be an apply term.
適用、つまり呼び出しはApplyというTermになる。
So apply on this method and the list of arguments.
このメソッドに対してApplyを呼び、引数のリストを渡す。
So this is going to be list with and we need a list of terms.
Termのリストが必要だ。
So the app, the apply gives us the arguments as a list of arbitrary terms.
Applyは引数を任意のTermのリストとして受け取る。
So I'm going to take the argument, which is an expert int and turn that into a term as well.
引数のExpr[Int]もTermに変換する必要がある。
So I'm going to say arg dot as term.
arg.asTermと書くんだ。
So this is the same as me calling instance dot method on the arguments.
これはinstance.method(arguments)と呼ぶのと同じことだ。
But the method name is not known, at least at this point.
ただ、メソッド名がこの時点ではわかっていないだけ。
The select dot unique makes the compiler search for this method and then invoke it with an apply.
Select.uniqueでコンパイラにこのメソッドを探させて、Applyで呼び出すんだ。
By the way, the select type and the apply type are both kinds of abstract syntax trees that the compiler can then inject back.
ちなみに、Select型もApply型も、コンパイラが再注入できるASTの一種だよ。
So the invocation, which is the apply term, I can turn that back into an expert string by essentially upcasting it.
呼び出し結果であるApply Termは、アップキャストすることでExpr[String]に戻せる。
So I'm going to say the invocation dot and there is a method called as expert of as expert of string.
invocation.asExprOf[String]と書く。asExprOfっていうメソッドがあるんだ。
So this turns a term back to an expert string if I know for a fact that this term is an expert string.
これはTermをExpr[String]に戻す。このTermがExpr[String]であると確信している場合にね。
And at this level, when I'm using Scala to manipulate other Scala code, I kind of have to trust myself that the types are correctly mentioned here,
このレベル、つまりScalaで他のScalaコードを操作するレベルでは、型が正しく指定されていることを自分で信頼する必要がある。
because if the types are not, then we are going to get a compile error.
型が間違っていたら、コンパイルエラーになるからね。
Okay, so let me go save this.
OK、保存しよう。
And the macros demo usage seems to also have been compiled.
マクロデモの使用側もコンパイルされたみたいだ。
Let's check the compiler output.
コンパイラ出力を確認しよう。
So look at this, the result is of type string, and we have a little block here.
見てみて。resultはString型で、小さなブロックがあるよ。
So look at this, we have instance proxy one, which is simple wrapper dot apply 10.
見てみて、instanceProxy1があって、SimpleWrapper.apply(10)になってる。
Okay, and then we have instance proxy one dot magic method on the meaning of life.
そしてinstanceProxy1.magicMethod(meaningOfLife)だ。
In other words, the compiler figured out that the result is simple wrapper 10, which is the intermediate method that you see here instance proxy one.
つまりコンパイラは、resultがSimpleWrapper(10)であることを解決した。ここに見えるinstanceProxy1がそれだ。
So simple wrapper 10, and then calling the magic method on that.
SimpleWrapper(10)を作って、そのmagicMethodを呼んでる。
So simple wrapper 10 dot magic method on meaning of life.
SimpleWrapper(10).magicMethod(meaningOfLife)ということだ。
So this was figured out, so found at compile time.
これがコンパイル時に解決されたんだ。
This is super important and super, super powerful.
これはめちゃくちゃ重要で、めちゃくちゃパワフルだよ。
It maintains the strength of the Scala language and the type system without having to compromise on the flexibility of calling or invoking things by name.
Scala言語と型システムの強さを維持しながら、名前でメソッドを呼び出す柔軟性を犠牲にしなくて済むんだ。
Obviously, if I have something that doesn't exist, like result invalid, let's say magic method two, this thing doesn't compile.
もちろん、存在しないものを呼んだら、例えばresultInvalidでmagicMethod2とすると、コンパイルできない。
So result invalid should not compile and we do get this sort of error.
resultInvalidはコンパイルできないはずで、実際にエラーが出る。
So value magic method two is not a member of simple wrapper.
「value magicMethod2 is not a member of SimpleWrapper」だ。
Okay, that's because the macro expansion tries to invoke the instance dot method two on the argument.
マクロ展開がinstance.magicMethod2(argument)を呼び出そうとするからだ。
And of course, that method does not exist.
当然、そのメソッドは存在しない。
So the code does not compile and that is expected.
だからコンパイルできない。想定通りだよ。
So macros are extremely powerful in Scala three, there is literally no parallel in other programming language to the kind of power and flexibility and also safety that the Scala macros offers in the same language with the same data structures, and with the power of the Scala compiler and this video only scratched the surface.
Scala 3のマクロは極めてパワフルだ。同じ言語、同じデータ構造、そしてScalaコンパイラのパワーを使って、ここまでの力と柔軟性と安全性を提供するプログラミング言語は他にないよ。この動画はほんの表面をなぞっただけだ。
If you want to learn more about this stuff, check out the Scala macros and metaprogramming course.
もっと学びたいなら、Scalaマクロ＆メタプログラミングコースをチェックしてね。
And in the meantime, I'm waiting for you with other videos and topics about pretty much everything there is to know about Scala functional programming Kotlin and everything else on Rock the Java.
その間も、Scalaや関数型プログラミング、Kotlinなど、あらゆるトピックの動画をRock the JVMでお届けするよ。
Until next time, folks, this was Daniel signing off.
それじゃまた次回。Danielでした。